[Music]
John kiraku was a CIA analyst was a and
case officer was a senior investigator
for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee a counterterrorism consultant
for ABC News and an author he was the
first US government official to confirm
in December 2007 that water boarding was
used to interrogate Al-Qaeda prisoners
and he described this as torture
on October 22nd 2012 kiraku was
sentenced to 30 months in federal prison
not for torture but for talking about
torture over his decision to blow the
whistle on the cia's post 911 torture
tactics John
kiraku thank you good morning I spent 15
years at the CIA and I would like to
speak with you this morning about
something that I witnessed uh in the
runup to the Iraq War and that was a
thirst for war a thirst for war that I
had never witnessed before in my in my
career or indeed in my
life I spent the first half of my career
as an analyst at the CIA uh working
entirely on Iraq in 1991 in the
immediate aftermath of the Iraqi
invasion of Kuwait I met Ahmed chelby
Ahmed chelby was an Iraqi
kurd a Shiite kurd which was unusual he
and his family had left Iraq in 1965 for
Jordan chelby made something of himself
he went to the University of Chicago he
had a PhD from MIT a degree from the
London School of economics and he
founded a bank in Jordan called Petra
bank which he immediately began to
loot he stole something like $36
million mostly from Iraqi refugees and
retirees people who had fled uh Iraq
over the years or who had retired in
Iraq I'm sorry who had retired in Jordan
he essentially stole their life
savings but the CIA identified Ahmed
chalabi as somebody who ought to be the
president of Iraq why because he served
the cia's purposes at least in
1991 chelby went on later that year to
found the Iraqi National Congress a
group of Yes Men uh active in Iraqi
opposition circles almost entirely in
the west most of the members of the
Iraqi National Congress hadn't been to
Iraq in decades but as I said they had
been identified as people that
Washington would like to see running the
country once chelby was made president
of the Iraqi National Congress the CIA
began to notice some things number one
nothing chelby ever said was true
he lied about absolutely
everything in addition the millions of
dollars of taxpayer money that was going
to finance the Iraqi National Congress
began to
disappear at the same time chelby bought
a multi-million dollar townhouse in
nightsbridge
London finally the CIA issued something
called a Burn Notice on chelby meaning
that no CIA officer was allowed to have
contact with him because he could not be
trusted he was a liar and a
thief 11 years later in
2002 I was told having just returned
from Pakistan that I would be working on
a compartmented program I was not even
allowed to know what my job was going to
be until I signed a separate secrecy
agreement I went up to the cia's sixth
floor and actually signed a series of
secrecy agreements six of them
once I had finished I said to the man
reading me into the compartment so what
gives and he looked at me and said well
here's the
story early next year we're going to
invade Iraq we're going to overthrow
Saddam Hussein and we're going to open
the world's largest Air Force Base in
southern Iraq we're going to move all of
our air assets out of Saudi Arabia into
Iraq thus deny denying Osama Bin Laden
the ability to say that we're polluting
the land of the two holy
mosques I was so stunned by this
ridiculous Revelation that all I could
think to say was but we haven't caught
Bin Laden
yet and this officer told me that the
battle lines had already been
drawn he said the decision was made and
there were two
camps the war was being pushed
specifically by the office of the vice
president president that was Dick Cheney
at the time the office of the Secretary
of Defense Donald Rumsfeld and the
National Security
Council he said CIA The Joint Chiefs and
the state department didn't want to do
it but being good soldiers we saluted
and said yes Mr
President a day later I walked into the
same man's office and he was sitting at
his desk with a blank piece of white
paper and some Crayola crayon
markers just to make conversation I said
what are you doing he said I'm designing
the new Iraqi
flag I said don't you think the Iraqis
should design the new Iraqi flag it
actually hadn't occurred to him that the
Iraqi people should design their
flag in the following weeks it became
clear to me that Ahmed chalabi was going
to have a role in whatever came out of
the muck and Meer that we had turned
Iraq into
the CIA rejected him as I said there was
a Burn Notice against him but chelby
began appearing in Washington regularly
at parties in
Georgetown at the Pentagon at the office
of the vice
president because the CIA had rejected
him chelby decided to activate his quote
unquote Army of intelligence operatives
and to report directly to the vice
president's office
but we all knew that chelby was a liar
the only thing chelby cared about was
chelby and he cared about becoming
president of Iraq and so he told
Cheney's staff and rumsfeld's staff and
rumsfeld's chain of command beneath him
that was created just to invade Iraq and
to handle
intelligence exactly what they wanted to
hear none of it was based in the truth
and there was a quidd pro quo the quidd
pro quo was I'll give you the
intelligence you need to convince the
American people and the US Congress that
you need to go to war and when this is
all done you make me president of
Iraq Cheney and Rumsfeld
agreed celibe knew that the
administration was obsessed with two
issues weapons of mass destruction and
terrorism
he also knew that there were no weapons
of mass destruction in
Iraq so he just simply manufactured the
intelligence I remember specifically one
night that I had been called into the
cia's Operation
Center Joe Wilson who had been Char
defair at the US Embassy in Baghdad in
the early 1990s had been sent to nier to
speak with the government of ner to ask
if it was true if rumors were true that
the Iraqis had sought the purchase of
yellow cake uranium Joe Wilson had been
ambassador to ner after he left uh Iraq
and the government of nier said that
none of it was true that the Iraqis had
not sent an emissary and certainly they
had not the N neran government had not
received any uh request for the purchase
of yellow cake
uranium Joe Wilson wrote this uh up in
the New York Times as an oped and of
course his wife uh Valerie pl's career
was later destroyed by it but I I was
called into CIA headquarters to to
review a document that the CIA had
received from a friendly intelligence
service that seemed to
corroborate cheli's story I went in to
look at this
document within five seconds anyone who
had ever served in any intelligence
capacity in the US government could see
that this document was a forgery it
wasn't even formatted correctly
I mean there were spelling errors and
grammatical errors and it was obviously
patched together by someone who had no
idea how this kind of thing
worked I said it was a
forgery the cia's Iraq analysts agreed
it was a
forgery it was clear that the Iraqis had
not sought yellow cake uranium from the
government of
ner but chelby didn't care what the CIA
said chelby cared only that the vice
president and the Secretary of Defense
were
happy chelby also passed information to
Cheney and Rumsfeld indicating that
there was a connection between Saddam
Hussein and Osama Bin Laden between the
government of Iraq and Al-Qaeda nothing
could have been any more
ridiculous than
that there was a famous story from the
1980s when Saddam Hussein had made the
minor pilgrimage the umra uh to
Mecca he didn't even know the prayers to
say and his vice president at the time
ISAT Ibrahim had to kneel behind him and
Whisper the prayers to him so that he
could repeat them out loud Sadam Hussein
wasn't a Muslim he was a
secularist there was no reason for
Saddam Hussein to have any connection
with Al-Qaeda or Osama Bin Laden and
indeed Bin Laden had made comments over
the years that he hated Saddam Hussein
as much as he hated the United
States so this connection Muhammad ATA
allegedly going to Prague to meet with
the the station chief of the Iraqi
intelligence service there was just made
up out of whole cloth because he knew
chelbe knew that it was a red button
issue that would help to push us into
war that's exactly what
happened George W bush tried to install
Ahmed chelby as the president of Iraq
once we had invaded But we had already
in such a short period of time made such
a colossal mess out of the place that
even the
Iraqis wouldn't accept him as president
unfortunately he did get something he
became the oil
Minister that's not the crime in this
whole thing Ahmed chelby promoting
himself the crime is that bush Cheney
and Rumsfeld knew all along that the
intelligence was phony they were just
looking for a pretext for war and they
knew that many Americans are too stupid
or too disinterested to challenge any of
this they were looking for a trigger
that would allow them to inst their
warped neoconservative vision of
democracy in Iraq I remember
participating in a secure video
teleconference with the National
Security adviser the Secretary of
Defense it was chaired by vice president
Cheney I was a minor figure and so I was
a notetaker for the director of the CIA
sitting against the back
wall and I remember a very senior
official of this government saying in
complete seriousness as soon as we cross
the border they're going to throw
flowers at us
having no
understanding that we were invading a
sovereign country slaughtering its
people and he believed that we would be
greeted as as uh as friends and
liberators now the crime is that
millions of Iraqis were killed they were
wounded they were maimed they were
displaced thousands of Americans died
for nothing no good reason at all that's
the crime and that's why we're here
today it's up to all of us to demand
Justice even though time has passed no
no matter how much time has passed we
have to demand Justice thank you very
much for